Fraser Valley University Society fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Fraser Valley University Society fonds
1983 - 1998, predominant 1991 - 1998
F-171
Q104471147
2.52 m of textual records 47 photographs 27 slides 54 negatives 3 moving images
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Photographs are located in series 1 and 5; see series descriptions for file numbers. Moving images are stored on videocassettes which were digitized to create digital preservation copies. Moving images are located in series 5.
Fraser Valley University Society
The Fraser Valley University Society was established on February 5, 1991. Founding members of the Society included members of several Canadian Federation of University Women's clubs, particularly Karen Yong and Sharon Shilliday of the Delta University Women's Club; members of the Fraser Valley Real Estate Board; as well as individuals and representatives of organizations from communities throughout the Fraser Valley. Many of these individuals had been involved in a predecessor group, the Fraser South University Society, which had been established by Yong and Shilliday in November 1990.
The Society's mandate was to "ensure the development of appropriate legislation creating a new university in the Fraser Valley." The main purposes of the Society were: to further the development of university education in the Fraser Valley by encouraging the Provincial Government to legislate the establishment of an independent, degree-granting institution; to foster public education initiatives promoting the social, economic and cultural value of a university; to actively pursue excellence in university education for all communities in the Fraser Valley; and to improve access to university education.
The Society was headed by an elected Board of Directors. The Board of Directors appointed the following officer positions: President, Vice-President, Treasurer, and Secretary. Committees, headed by a Chair, were created to carry out the objectives of the Society. The original five committees of the society were the Public Relations Committee, Community Relations Committee, Fundraising Committee, Membership Committee, and the Government Committee. The first President of the Society was Karen Yong. She was succeeded in 1993 by Robert (Bob) Lowe, who remained President until the Society's dissolution. At its height, membership in the Society was over 1,100 members.
The Society enlisted the assistance of local government and community organizations in its efforts. From its inception, the Society received financial and other support, including office space in Surrey, from the Fraser Valley Real Estate Board. Other funds were obtained through government grant applications, membership fees, donations, and fundraising events. The Society also concentrated on promotional and community relations activities. Members collected over 7,000 petition signatures, set up information kiosks in malls and at public events, made presentations to local groups, solicited media coverage of Society events and activities, and distributed promotional material. The Society created and collaborated on several reports concerning the need for post-secondary education in the Fraser Valley, and established relationships with members of local and provincial governments.
In 1994 the Society began to place increased pressure on the Provincial Government and, after many meetings and much correspondence, Premier Mike Harcourt announced in February 1995 his government's support for the creation of a Technical University in the Fraser Valley (the Technical University of British Columbia). In May 1995 Society Board member Sharon Shilliday was appointed to the Interim Planning Council for the University; the Council became part of the Technical University Society of British Columbia when it was registered on August 10, 1995.
As a result of the Government's commitment to the creation of a new university, the Society evolved into a public foundation responsible for raising funds for the Technical University of British Columbia and its students. The Society's constitution was amended in August 1996 to reflect this change in mandate. In February 1998, a unanimous decision was made to dissolve the Society and transfer its fundraising responsibilities, as well as accumulated funds, assets, and records to the Technical University of British Columbia. Fundraising responsibilities were assumed by the University's new Vice-President External Affairs and Research. At an extraordinary meeting of the Society on April 28, 1998, the Society was dissolved.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
Fonds consists of records relating to the activities of the Fraser Valley University Society and its role in the establishment of the Technical University of British Columbia. Activities, events, and topics documented include the formation of the Society; the Society's organization, structure and membership; general administration and correspondence; management of the Society's budget and financial resources; Board, committee, and other meetings; community outreach and promotion; fundraising; research; and the Society's development of relationships with municipal and provincial government bodies.
Records include correspondence; minutes and agendas; organizational charts, constitutions, by-laws, mission statements, policies and procedures; budgets and financial statements; reports; subject files; member and donor lists; speeches; newsletters, promotional brochures and flyers; press releases and newspaper articles; videocassettes; and photographs and slides.
The original order of the records comprising the fonds was not discernible. In order to facilitate access to the material, the archivist created series based on the functions and activities of the Society. The archivist also arranged loose material into folders where necessary.
Yong, Karen; Technical University of British Columbia; Fraser Valley Real Estate Board; Lowe, Robert; Photographic materials; Moving images; Textual records; Education
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Technical University of British Columbia on July 17, 2002.
All accessions have been processed as of June 2004. No further accruals are expected.
The records remained in the custody and control of the Society until its dissolution in 1998, at which time they were transferred into the custody and control of the Technical University of British Columbia.
For other material relating to the Fraser Valley University Society, see the finding aid to the Technical University of British Columbia fonds.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Access to videocassettes is restricted due to fragility of the medium. Access is provided via digital access copies. Consult the reference archivist for more details about accessing moving images in this fonds.
File and item lists are available. See appendices to this finding aid.
- Organization and administration records, 1991 - 1997; F-171-1; 21 cm of textual records 22 photographs 39 negatives; General note: photographs are located in files F-171-1-0-0-22.1 (6 photos) and F-171-1-0-0-15.1 (16 photos).
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the founding, organization, mandate, scope of activities and general administration of the Fraser Valley University Society. Activities, events and topics documented include the development of the Society's constitution, bylaws, goals, and policies; job descriptions; applications for charitable status, a casino licence and government funding; as well as volunteer efforts and management. Series also includes some records relating to the organization and administration of the Technical University of British Columbia. Activities, events and topics documented include the University's relationship with the Fraser Valley University Society and the Provincial Government, and the funding of the University.
  Records include organizational charts, constitution and bylaws, mission statements, policies and procedures, job descriptions, correspondence, forms, applications, resolutions, biographical material, photographs, lists, calendars, and phone logs.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Board members - biographies, 1992 - 1995; F-171-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Board of Directors - biographies, 1995 - 1996; F-171-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Board - Karen Yong, 1992 - 1993; F-171-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Board - policy manual, 1991; F-171-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Board - potential members, 1997; F-171-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Board of Directors - volunteer time, 1992; F-171-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Administration - calendar copy, 1991 - 1992; F-171-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Casino application - 1997, 1991 - 1997; F-171-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Charitable application, 1996 - 1997; F-171-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Charitable donations - information, 1991 - 1997; F-171-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - New application for charity status, April 1992, 1991 - 1993; F-171-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - CJS project - attendance records, 1991 - 1992; F-171-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Constitution, 1996; F-171-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - CUPE resolution, 1992; F-171-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Membership - bylaws, 1991; F-171-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Members - photographs, 1991; F-171-1-0-0-15.1; Physical description: 16 photographs and 39 negatives. (Archival box - small 171-20)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Mission statements and goals, 1992; F-171-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Organizational chart, 1991; F-171-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Original documents, 1993; F-171-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Originals, 1991 - 1992; F-171-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Personnel - job descriptions, 1992; F-171-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 171-1)
  - Phone logs, 1993 - 1995; F-171-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Photos / biographies - Tech BC, 1996; F-171-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Photos / biographies - Tech BC, vol. 2, 1996; F-171-1-0-0-22.1; Physical description: 6 photographs and 5 negatives. (Archival box - small 171-20)
  - Policy manual, 1992 - 1993; F-171-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Society Act, 1994; F-171-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Tech BC - correspondence, 1996 - 1997; F-171-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Volunteer appreciation / recognition, 1991; F-171-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Volunteers, 1991 - 1993; F-171-1-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
- General correspondence, 1991 - 1997; F-171-2; 75 cm of textual records
  Series consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence of the Society. Includes correspondence between members, as well as correspondence with government and school officials, community organizations, business associations, media, and post-secondary institutions. Activities, events and topics documented include special events, promotion, fundraising, co-operation and liaison, government relations, and general administrative activities.
  Records include letters, memoranda, faxes and related attachments such as press releases, promotional material and minutes.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist.
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence, vol. 3, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence, vol. 4, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence, vol. 5, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence, vol. 6, February 1991 - March 1992; F-171-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 171-2)
  - Correspondence - 1992, vol. 1, 1991 - 1992; F-171-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence - 1992, vol. 2, 1991 - 1992; F-171-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence - 1992, vol. 3, 1991 - 1992; F-171-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, 1991 - 1997; F-171-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Administration - 20/20 Vision, 1992; F-171-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, 1992; F-171-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 3, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 4, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 5, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence, vol. 6, 1992 - 1994; F-171-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 171-3)
  - Correspondence - in, 1993; F-171-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 1, 1993; F-171-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 2, 1993; F-171-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - in, vol. 1, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - in, vol. 2, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 1, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 2, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 3, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - in, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - out, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 171-4)
  - Correspondence - in, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 1, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Correspondence - out, vol. 2, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Correspondence, April 1997 - June 1997; F-171-2-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Correspondence, August 1997; F-171-2-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Correspondence - Tech BC, July 1997; F-171-2-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - E-mail, 1997; F-171-2-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Kekinow, June 1997; F-171-2-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Administration - memos, 1991; F-171-2-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Administration - memos, 1992; F-171-2-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Administration - memos, 1993; F-171-2-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Administration - memos, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Memos, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Memos, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Administration - faxes - incoming, December 1991 - December 1993; F-171-2-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 1, 1991 - 1993; F-171-2-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 2, 1991 - 1993; F-171-2-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 3, 1991 - 1993; F-171-2-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 171-5)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 4, 1991 - 1993; F-171-2-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 5, 1991 - 1993; F-171-2-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - in, vol. 1, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-49 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - in, vol. 2, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-50 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - in, vol. 3, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-51 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 1, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-52 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 2, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-53 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 3, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-54 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 4, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-55 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 5, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-56 (Archival box - standard 171-6)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 6, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-57 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 7, 1994; F-171-2-0-0-58 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 1, 1 January 1994 - 31 March 1994; F-171-2-0-0-59 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 2, 1 January 1994 - 31 March 1994; F-171-2-0-0-60 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 3, 1 January 1994 - 31 March 1994; F-171-2-0-0-61 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 4, 1 January 1994 - 31 March 1994; F-171-2-0-0-62 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - in, vol. 1, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-63 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - in, vol. 2, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-64 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 1, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-65 (Archival box - standard 171-7)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 2, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-66 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 3, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-67 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 4, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-68 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 5, 1995; F-171-2-0-0-69 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - in, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-70 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 1, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-71 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Faxes - outgoing, vol. 2, 1996; F-171-2-0-0-72 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
- Financial records, 1991 - 1997; F-171-3; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of financial records of the Society. Activities, events and topics documented include budget preparation, allocation and use of financial resources, and funding and grant requests.
  Records include budgets and financial statements, as well as applications for government funding, and related supporting papers.
  - Accounting - budget, 1992; F-171-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Accounting - financial statements, 1992 - 1996; F-171-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Financial statements, 1997; F-171-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Grants - municipal, 1991 - 1996; F-171-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Grants - requests, 1994 - 1997; F-171-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Challenge '92, 1992; F-171-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Board meetings - info [job creation], 1991; F-171-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Job development / creation, 1991 - 1992; F-171-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
  - Job creation budget forecast, 1992; F-171-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 171-8)
- Board, committee and meeting records, 1990 - 1998; F-171-4; 38 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to meetings of the Board of Directors, several committees (including the Executive Committee, Fundraising Committee, Government Relations Committee, Strategy Committee and Advisory Committee) and ad-hoc or extraordinary meetings. In addition to some minutes of the Society's predecessor body, the Fraser South University Society, the series also includes records relating to meetings of the society with other groups, including meetings of the Joint Committee Group, the University of Surrey Community Committee and the Langley Economic Development Commission.
  Records include meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers, correspondence, reports, budgets, financial statements, and special resolutions.
  For other records relating to committee activities, see also the following series: Community relations, promotion and fundraising records, Government relations records and Membership records.
  - Advisory Committee appointees, 1991; F-171-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - AGM minutes, 1992 - 1996; F-171-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - AGM, 1993; F-171-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - annual general meeting 1994, 1993 - 1994; F-171-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - annual general meeting 1995, F-171-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Annual general meeting 1996, 1995 - 1997; F-171-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Annual general meeting 1997, 1996 - 1997; F-171-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - minutes of meetings [board] 1991, F-171-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Board meetings 1992, F-171-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - minutes of meetings [board] 1992, F-171-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - minutes of meetings [board] 1993, F-171-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Administration - minutes of meetings [board] 1994, F-171-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Minutes [board], 1995; F-171-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Minutes [board], 1996; F-171-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Minutes [board] 1997, vol. 1, 1997 - 1998; F-171-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Minutes [board] 1997, vol. 2, 1997 - 1998; F-171-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Minutes and rough notes [board], 1997; F-171-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 171-9)
  - Board committee reports, 1996; F-171-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - monthly committee reports - community [relations], 1991 - 1994; F-171-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - monthly committee reports - fundraising, 1992 - 1996; F-171-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - monthly committee reports - government [relations], 1992 - 1994; F-171-4-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - monthly committee reports - membership, 1992 - 1995; F-171-4-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - monthly committee reports - public [relations], 1991 - 1995; F-171-4-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - retreat information, 1991 - 1992; F-171-4-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Board members - retreat, 1992; F-171-4-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Board - special resolutions, 1993; F-171-4-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Administration - minutes of meetings (Executives), 1991 - 1993; F-171-4-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - F.V.U.S., 1998; F-171-4-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Langley Economic Development Commission, 1991 - 1992; F-171-4-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 171-10)
  - Minutes, correspondence and supporting papers, vol. 1, 1990 - 1991; F-171-4-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 171-10)